翻譯：艾瑞卡  回風舞雪兮  木淺薰
翻譯：Reginamoon  小蠻腰
校對：珞珞  Panda
總監：somehacker
后期：BOGLFT
這里是博克島
This is Berk,
這里的神秘感可謂是
the best kept secret this side of, well...
舉世無雙
Anywhere.
當然  可能看起來并不起眼
Granted, it may not look like much,
但這潮濕的巖石群中
but this wet heap of rock
卻藏著不少驚喜
packs more than a few surprises.
這里的生活精彩絕倫
Life here is amazing,
只是不適合膽小鬼們
just not for the faint of heart.
要知道  其他地方的人都喜歡削削木頭
You see, where most folks enjoy hobbies like whittling
或者繡繡花什么的  而我們博克島人則喜歡
or needlepoint, we Berkians prefer...
一種小小的娛樂活動  名為
a little something we like to call...
賽龍
dragon racing!
抱歉啦  小魚腳  你是想要這個嗎
I'm sorry, Fishlegs, did you want that?
鼻涕嘮  那是我的
Oh, Snotlout, that was mine!
寶貝  給你
Here you go, babe.
我有說過你今天看上去很美嗎
Did I tell you that you look amazing today?
因為你真的很美
Cause you do.
走吧  噴噴
Come on, Barf.
臭味都傳到我這兒來了
It's starting to stink around here.
放棄吧  她還是討厭你
Nope, still hates you.
讓這里燃起來吧  吐吐
Let's blow this place, Belch!
走著
All right!
加油
Come on!
好樣的
Oh, yeah!
雙胞胎得九分
That's nine for the twins!
艾絲翠得三分緊隨其后
Astrid lags with three!
小魚腳和鼻涕嘮各得零分墊底
Fishlegs and Snotlout trail with none!
然后小嗝嗝
And Hiccup is...
還是不見蹤影
nowhere to be found.
你的促膝談心是不是嚇到他了  史推克
Scared him off with the big talk, didn't you, Stoick?
你在干什么  鼻涕嘮
What are you doing, Snotlout?
他們要贏了
They're gonna win now.
她是我的女神  她有求  我必應
She's my princess... whatever she wants, she gets.
暴芙奈  她不是想把你活埋來著嗎
Ruffnut? Didn't she try to bury you alive?
也就埋了幾個小時
Only for a few hours.
快看他們  沖啊
Look at 'em, go!
龍曾是這里的
Now, dragons used to be
頭號公敵
a bit of a problem here,
但那都是五年前的事了
but that was five years ago.
現在他們都在島上定居了
Now they've all moved in.
說真的  他們有什么理由不搬來這呢
And, really, why wouldn't they?
我們有定制的龍舍
We have custom stables,
全天供應的自助餐
all-you-can-eat feeding stations,
全方位的龍浴服務
a full-service dragon wash...
甚至還有最先進的火災應對措施
Even top-of-the-line fire prevention,
我這么自夸請別見怪
if I do say so myself.
是時候了  戈伯
Ah, it's time, Gobber.
好的  最后一輪
Righty-ho. Last lap!
是黑羊  上吧  風中飛
The black sheep! Come on, Stormfly!
我們還有機會贏得比賽
We can still win this thing!
-來吧  噴噴  -我們走
- Come on, Barf! -Let's go!
上啊  肉球
Go, Meatlug!
快飛  快飛
Let's go, let's go!
該你上場了
This is your big moment.
祝你旅途愉快
Have a nice flight.
往上  往上  往上
Up! Up, up, up, up, up!
干得好  肉球
Good job, Meatlug!
給你  親愛的  我的這個值十分
Here you go, darling. Mine's worth ten.
太好了  黑羊
Yeah! The black sheep!
你們兩個在爭暴芙奈嗎
You guys are fighting for Ruffnut?
-我贏定了  -是我們倆一起贏
- I'm totally winning! - We're winning together.
不
Oh, no!
-我現在無人可擋了  -除了我
- Whoo! No one can stop me now! - Except for me.
我們是連在一起的  蠢材
We're attached, genius.
別想把我的榮耀偷走
Quit trying to steal all my glory!
-搞定他們  艾絲翠  -是我的榮耀
- Get them, Astrid! - It's my glory!
-成事不足敗事有余  -沒羊就沒榮耀
- Always ruining everything! - No sheep, no glory!
抓到了
Gotcha! Ha-ha!
艾絲翠
Whoa! Astrid!
干得漂亮
Well played!
那是我未來的兒媳婦
That's my future daughter-in-law!
抱歉了
Uh, excuse me.
風中飛
Stormfly!
一共十三分
That's 13!
艾絲翠贏得了比賽
Astrid takes the game!
沒錯  博克島堪稱完美
Yep, Berk is pretty much perfect.
我最終得償所愿
All of my hard work has paid off.
而且這也是件好事
And it's a good thing, too,
維京人能馭龍翱翔之后
because with Vikings on the backs of dragons...
世界也變得遼闊了許多
...the world just got a whole lot bigger.
好贊
Yeah!
怎么樣  伙計
So, what do you think, bud?
想再試一次嗎
You want to give this another shot?
沒牙仔  不會有事的
Toothless! It'll be fine.
準備好了嗎
Ready?
好耶
Yeah!
棒
這感覺太棒了
This is amazing!
現在不棒了
No longer amazing.
沒牙仔
Toothless!
不好
Oh, no!
剛剛真是始料未及
That really came out of nowhere.
我們得再訓練下你的單獨滑行  伙計
We-we got to work on your solo gliding there, bud.
那個固定尾翼
That, uh, locked-up tail
真不方便進行救援行動  是吧
makes for some pretty sloppy rescue maneuvers, hey?
看來我們又找到一處  伙計
Looks like we found another one, bud.
怎么  你想要我道歉嗎
Oh, what, do you want an apology?
就因為這個在生悶氣嗎
Is that why you're pouting,
小傻瓜
big baby boo?
試試這個
Well, try this on!
感受到了嗎
Oh, you feeling it yet? Huh?
感受到我真誠的歉意了嗎
Picking up on all my heartfelt remorse?
好了  得了  別這樣
Ah. Yeah. Oh, come on, come on,
你不會想殘害一個獨腿的...
you-you wouldn't hurt a one-legged...
你是對的  你是對的
Y-you're right, you're right.
你贏了  你贏了
You win. You win.
他倒下了
He's down!
一場惡斗
And it's ugly!
龍和維京人
Dragons and vikings...
再次為敵
Enemies again...
戰況愈演愈烈
Locked in combat to the bitter...
你知道口水洗不掉
You know that doesn't wash out.
我們給這里取什么名字好呢
So, what should we name it?
那就叫癢胳肢窩島吧
"Itchy armpit" It is.
你覺得怎么樣  伙計
What do you reckon, bud?
也許能在樹林里找到幾只割木龍
Think we might find a few Timberjacks in those woods?
或者在巖石群里找到些致命耳語龍
The odd Whispering Death or two in the rocks?
誰知道呢  或許我們最終能找到
Who knows, maybe we'll finally track down
第二只夜煞
another Night Fury.
那可真是大發現
Wouldn't that be something.
你覺得呢
So, what do you say?
我們繼續前進
Just keep going?
下午好  小姐
Afternoon, milady.
-你去哪了  -你好啊
- Where have you been? - Hi.
贏了幾場比賽  不然呢
Oh, winning races. What else?
真正該問的是
The real question is,
你都去哪了
where have you been?
-躲我爸爸  -不是吧  又怎么了
- Avoiding my dad. - Oh, no. What happened now?
你肯定愛聽這段
Oh, you're gonna... You're gonna love this.
我一早醒來  陽光明媚
I wake up, the sun's shining,
屋頂上有幾只
Terrible Terrors are
恐怖龍在唱歌
singing on the rooftop,
我優哉游哉地下樓吃早飯
I saunter down to breakfast
想著世界上一切安好  結果我聽到
thinking all is right with the world, and I get:
兒子  我們得談談
"Son, we need to talk."
現在不行  爸爸  我一整天
"Not, now, dad. I got a whole day of goofing off
都得忙著去瞎轉悠呢
to get started."
好吧  首先
Okay, first of all,
我說話聲音才不那樣  你到底在模仿誰
I-I don't sound like that. What is this character?
其次
And-and second...
我才不會那樣聳肩膀呢
What is that thing you're doing with my shoulders?
這也太夸張吧
Yeah, that's-that's a really flattering impersonation.
言歸正傳啊  他說
Anyway, he goes...
你是博克島的驕傲  兒子
"You're the pride of Berk, son,
-我也以你為榮  -謝謝  爸爸
- and I couldn't be prouder." - "Aw, thanks, dad.
我也覺得自己很厲害
I'm pretty impressed with myself, too.
我什么時候變得這么愛揮手了
When have I ever done that with my hands?
你剛剛還那么做呢
You just did!
好吧  你就...
Okay, just...
先別動
Hold... still.
很嚴肅的
Very serious.
你也長大成人了
"You're all grown up,
既然你已經證明了自己能夠委以重任
and since no chief could ask for a better successor,
-我決定...  -讓你當部落首領  老天
- I've decided..." - To make you chief! Oh, my gods!
小嗝嗝  這太棒了
Hiccup, that's amazing!
頻繁使用彈簧圈會磨損
Y-you're gonna wear out the spring coil.
很難校準的
The calibration is very sensitive.
沒錯  這就是
Yeah, so... this is
我現在頭疼的事
what I'm dealing with.
你怎么答復他的
What did you tell him?
我沒答復他
I-I didn't.
等他轉過身來  我已經跑了
By the time he turned around, I was gone.
好吧  你已經身負重任了
Well... it's a lot of responsibility.
畫地圖的事肯定得暫時擱置
The map will have to wait, for sure,
如果以后你沒有時間的話
and... and I'll need
就得由我來飛沒牙仔  可是
to fly Toothless, since you'll be too busy, but...
我無法勝任  艾絲翠
I-it's not me, Astrid.
那些演講啊  規劃啊  還有管理村莊
All those speeches and planning and running the village,
那是他的長項
that's his thing.
你沒理解重點
I think you're missing the point.
我是說  當首領
I mean... chief.
多么榮耀
What an honor!
換我肯定激動死了
I'd be pretty excited.
但我不像你
I-I... I'm not like you.
你一直知道自己想要的是什么
You... know exactly who you are,
你一直都是  但是
you always have, but...
我還在找尋自己的方向
I'm still looking.
我知道自己不會像父親那樣
I know that I'm not my father,
我也沒見過我母親
and I never met my mother, so...
那我究竟該成為怎樣的人呢
What does that make me?
你要找尋的并不在遠方  小嗝嗝
What you're searching for isn't out there, Hiccup...
就在這里
It's in here.
也許只是你還沒認識到而已
Maybe you just don't see it yet.
也許吧
Maybe.
但是
But, you know...
遠方好像有什么東西
there is something out there.
小嗝嗝
Hiccup...
跟緊我
Stay close.
這里發生了什么
What happened here?
好了  放松  伙計
All right, e-easy, bud.
小嗝嗝
Hiccup!
-發射  -艾絲翠  小心
- Fire! - Astrid, look out!
小嗝嗝
Aah! Hiccup!
小心尾巴
Watch the tail!
把腿綁住
Tie those legs up!
-那不會是真的吧  -住手
- Is that what I think it is? - Stop!
風中飛
Stormfly!
你們要干什么
What are you doing?!
出現了
Back again!
我的老天
Soil my britches.
還真是一只夜煞
That is a Night Fury.
還以為他們都絕跡了
Thought they were all gone for good.
看來我們交上好運了  伙計們
Looks like our luck's had a turn for the better, lads!
德拉戈的龍族大軍里
Don't think Drago has one of those...
肯定還沒有夜煞呢
in his dragon army.
龍族大軍
Dragon army?
聽著  我們不想惹麻煩
Look, we don't want any trouble.
你在偷走我們所有的龍
Hah! You should have thought of that
并且摧毀我們的堡壘之前
before you stole all of our dragons
就該想到這點
and blasted our fort to bits!
-沒錯  -對  你瞧瞧
- That's right! - Yeah, look at it!
等等
Wait.
你們在說什么
What are you talking about?
你覺得這是我們干的嗎
You think we did this?
捕龍這活兒本身已經夠困難了
Hah! Dragon trapping is hard enough work as it is
結果還遇上個行俠仗義的龍騎士
without do-gooder dragon riders
-偷偷摸摸地救龍搗亂  -什么行俠仗義的...
- sneaking in to rescue them. - What do-gooder...?
還有別的龍騎士嗎
There are other dragon riders?
除了你那個盜龍的朋友嗎  你說呢
You mean other than your thieving friend from last night? You tell me.
你也許有只能噴冰的龍給你撐腰
You may have an ice-spitting dragon on your side,
但我們必須得完成我們的捕龍指標
but we still have a quota to fill.
你要我們怎么跟德拉戈·布達威斯
How do you suppose we explain this mess
解釋這爛攤子
to Drago Bludvist?
德拉戈什么
Drago what-fist?
你說的這些都是什么意思
Does anything you say make sense?
他正等著明天我們為他的龍族大軍
He's expecting a new shipment of dragons
擴充一群新成員
for his army by tomorrow.
德拉戈不喜歡聽借口
And Drago don't take well to excuses!
上回空手回去
This is what he gave me
他就給了我這個
last time I showed up empty-handed.
他說以后就不會這么手下留情了
He promised to be far less understanding in the future.
好了  聽著  我們沒聽過什么盜龍賊
All right, look, we don't know anything about a dragon thief
什么噴冰龍
or an ice-spitting dragon
或者你那個瘋子老板
or your lunatic boss
還有他的龍族大軍  好嗎
and his dragon army, okay?
只要把我們的龍還回來  我們就離開
Just give us back our dragon, and we'll go...
我們從沒見過這么兇巴巴的怪人
Strange, hostile person whom we've never met.
我的禮貌都去哪了
Oh, where are my manners?
我叫艾瑞特
I'm Eret...
和我父親同名
Son of Eret.
世上最好的捕龍獵手
Finest dragon trapper alive.
畢竟
After all...
夜煞不是人人都能抓到的
it's not just anyone who can capture a Night Fury.
他叫沒牙仔
And this is Toothless.
他說我們現在就離開
He says we're going. Now.
我們也等不及了
They all say that.
上  伙計們
Rush 'em, lads!
風中飛  快
Stormfly, come on!
撤  撤
Go! Go!
那些龍
You will
你是留不住的
never hold on to those dragons!
你聽到了嗎
You hear me?!
德拉戈會把它們全部搶走
Drago is coming for them all!
快點  肉球
Come on, Meatlug!
-你好  史推克  -你好
- Hey there, Stoick! - Hey, how are you?
天氣真好
Beautiful day.
你好  嫉妒嘮  比賽真棒
Hello, Spitelout. Great race. Yeah...
抱歉  艾克夫人
Oh! Sorry, Mrs. Ack.
-有他的消息嗎  -他現在可能已經
- Any sign of him? - Eh! He's probably flown
飛得無影無蹤了
off the edge of the world by now.
你確定想讓那娃管理村莊嗎
You sure you want that kid running the village?
你還有機會延遲退休
You can still delay your retirement.
他準備好了  你會明白的
Oh, he's ready. You'll see.
他來了
There he is!
博克島的驕傲
Huh? The pride of Berk!
你總算決定回來工作了
Who finally decided to show up for work. Yay.
抱歉  耽擱了
Sorry, got held up.
爸爸  能跟你聊兩句嗎
Hey, uh, dad, could I have a word?
有什么事等不及要告訴我了嗎
Something you're itching to tell me?
不是你想的那件事
Uh, not quite the itch you're thinking of,
不過  確實有事
but, yes.
好樣的
Oh, good man!
第一課  首領第一要務
Now, lesson one: A chief's first duty
就是服務于人民
is to his people,
所以  四十一號
so... 41!
我們能不能找個人少的地方聊聊
Well, can we just talk in private for...
-四十...  -是我
- Forty... - That's me!
是我  到我了
That's me! I'm next!
我排在你前面
Hey, I was ahead of you!
我們能不能談...
If we could just talk...
不好意思  我都在這兒等一天了
Excuse me. I've been here all day.
我想要一個高龍鞍
Okay, okay, I want one of those high seaters
打滿鐵釘的那種  還要帶一個大儲物箱
with lots of spikes and a big storage compartment!
-沒問題  保證給你  -爸爸  我要說的事
- Absolutely! You got it, sir. -Dad, this is actually
比造龍鞍更重要
a little more important than building saddles.
第二課  為人民服務
Ah, lesson two: No task is too small
不論大事小事
when it comes to serving your people.
-可是  爸爸  -抱歉  葛倫普
- But, dad... - Oh, excuse us, Grump.
-我們能不能談談  -葛倫普
- Can we just talk... - Yah! Grump!
你又讓鍛爐熄滅了
You let the forge die down again!
我受夠了  葛倫普  你就等著被別人領養吧
That's it, Grump! You're going up for adoption.
-好的  -給你
- Okay, uh... - There you go.
-爸爸  -動手吧
- Dad... - Go on. Have away.
說真的  我必須
Yeah, but seriously, I really need to
把我們發現新大陸的事告訴你
tell you about this new land we came across.
-新大陸  -有新品種的龍嗎
- Another one? - Any new dragons?
我們沒能仔細探索
We didn't stick around to find out.
那些人不太友好
These folks weren't particularly friendly.
是嗎
Oh, really?
你的夜煞還有致命納得
Your Night Fury and Deadly Nadder
沒讓他們樂翻天嗎
didn't bring them cheering to the rooftops?
這回不一樣
No, this was different.
沒有往常的興高采烈
Not the standard run-for-the-hills hoo-ha
和讓我陶醉的歡呼
I've come to enjoy.
那些人都是獵手
These guys were trappers.
捕龍獵手
Dragon trappers.
你應該看看他們的堡壘
You should have seen their fort.
完全炸裂開  卡在巨大的冰錐里
All blown apart and stuck in giant spikes of ice.
看上去無比怪異
It was weird.
我第一次見那樣的場面
I've never seen anything like it.
最糟糕的是  他們以為是我們干的
A-and worst of all, they thought we did it!
你們倆總有一天
You know, you two are gonna get yourselves
會給自己惹上大麻煩
in serious trouble one of these days.
并不是所有人都喜歡這種生活方式
Not everyone appreciates this way of life.
戈伯說得沒錯  兒子
Aye, Gobber's right, son.
我們最好待在自己家鄉
Best we keep to our own.
而且  你還有更重要的事要做
Besides, you'll have more important uses for your time.
只等我來宣布這個重磅消息了
Once we make the big announcement!
他們在組建龍族大軍
They are building a dragon army.
或者說他們的老板在組建龍族大軍
Or-or at least the guy they work for is. Uh...
叫什么德拉戈·被打威斯之類的
"Dargo... bloody fist" Or something.
要是他妄想搶走我的龍
I'll bloody his fist with my face
我就用我的臉血染他的拳頭
if he tries to take my dragon!
還有我的
Or mine!
你還真白癡
Ugh! You're such a moron.
白癡美女哦
A beautiful moron.
沒錯
Yeah.
布達威斯  德拉戈·布達威斯是嗎
Bludvist? Drago Bludvist?
沒錯  等等
Uh, yeah. Wait...
你認識他嗎
You know him?
-所有龍停飛  -什么  為什么
- Ground all dragons! - What? Why?
關上大門
Seal the gates!
-降下外門  -等等
- Lower the storm doors! - Whoa, whoa, whoa, wait, wait.
-怎么回事  -快點
- What is happening? - Come on!
聽命令  鎖門
You heard the man! Lock it down!
沒有我的命令
No dragon or viking
所有龍和維京人不準離開本島半步
sets foot off this island until I give the word!
等等  就因為你認識的某人在遙遠的
Wait, because some guy you knew is stirring up trouble
陸地制造麻煩嗎
in some faraway land?
因為德拉戈·布達威斯是個瘋子
Because Drago Bludvist is a madman
毫無道德和同情心可言
without conscience or mercy.
要是他組建了龍族大軍
And if he's built a dragon army,
我們最好早做準備
gods help us all.
-把它們送回籠子  -是  史推克
- Get them into their pens! - Aye, Stoick.
快
Quickly!
那我們就飛回去
Then let's ride back out there.
跟著那些捕龍獵手找到德拉戈
We'll follow those trappers to Drago
勸他理智些
and talk some sense into him.
不  我們要在島上建防御工事
No. We fortify the island.
維護和平是我們的責任
It's our duty to keep the peace.
和平結束了  小嗝嗝
Peace is over, Hiccup.
-我們必須為戰爭做好準備  -戰爭
- I must prepare you for war. - War?
爸爸  要是德拉戈來搶我們的龍
Dad, if Drago's coming for our dragons,
我們不能坐以待斃
we can't wait around for him to get here.
我們去找到他  勸他改變想法
Let's go find him and change his mind.
不  有些人是勸不動的  小嗝嗝
No, some minds won't be changed, Hiccup.
你要擔心的是博克島
Berk is what you need to worry about.
首領要保衛自己的領土
A chief protects his own.
保護龍廄  全部上鎖
Secure the stables! Latch every stall!
-小嗝嗝  別去  -我沒得選
- Hiccup, don't. - I have to.
這邊
This way!
快
Quickly!
小嗝嗝
Hiccup!
快
Come on!
小嗝嗝
Hiccup!
擦亮眼睛  伙計們
Keep your eyes peeled, lads!
借著這陣風  我們天亮就能找到德拉戈
With this wind, we'll reach Drago by daybreak.
所以我們最好把這艘船裝滿龍  要快
So best we fill this ship up with dragons, and quick!
沒時間挑剔了
It's no time to be picky!
艾瑞特
Uh, Eret?
要是我們不想腦袋搬家...
Not if we want to keep our...
就抓緊時間
...heads!
在左舷船尾
Off the port quarter!
網住它們  伙計們  把它們打下來
Net them, lads! Take them down!
共有兩只  在左上方
There's two of them! Up on the left!
這回你們逃不了了
You're not getting away this time.
開火
Fire!
裝彈  裝彈
Reload! Reload!
快  裝彈  有人入侵
Come on, reload! Incoming!
穩住了  伙計
Steady yourselves, mates.
剛才我還在擔心
And here I was,
我們會空手而歸呢
worried we might turn up empty-handed.
不會的  今天是你的幸運日
Nope. It's your lucky day.
我們投降
We give up.
這有條夜煞
That's one Night Fury,
一條致命納得
uh, one Deadly Nadder, and...
還有兩位技壓群雄的神秘龍騎士
Two of the finest dragon riders west of luk tuk.
這樣老板就能滿意了  是不是
That ought to make the boss happy, right?
借過
Excuse us.
你要干什么
What are you doing?
沒牙仔  別動
Toothless, stay.
龍其實不喜歡
Uh, the dragons don't really care
狹窄的空間  所以它們跟你們待一起好了
for cramped spaces, so they'll just hang out with you.
它們不會惹麻煩
They won't be any trouble.
除非你先挑事
Unless you do that.
汪洋大海上的一艘木帆
You know, wooden boats, big ocean...
你們的游泳技術怎么樣
H-how is your swimming?
不太好
Not good.
差點忘了
Oops. Almost forget.
-囚犯不能攜帶武器  -把它給我
- Can't have armed prisoners. - Give me that.
這算什么計劃
How is this a plan?
就是為捕龍獵人準備的
Just what every dragon trapper needs.
一邊是涂著兇煞夢魘唾液的長劍
One end coats the blade in Monstrous Nightmare saliva.
另一邊會噴射兇惡雙頭龍的瓦斯
The other sprays Hideous Zippleback gas.
只需一點火花然后...
All it takes is a spark, and...
沒錯  就會這樣
Oh, yeah, there you go.
它們一旦開始把你看作同類
Once they see you as one of their own,
那么就連最暴躁的龍都可以馴化
even the testiest dragons can be trained.
是吧  伙計
Right, bud?
把那個給我
Give me that!
你在玩什么把戲
What game are you playing?
不是把戲  我們只是想見德拉戈
Uh, no game. We just want to meet Drago.
為什么
Why?
因為我要改變他關于龍的想法
Because I'm going to change his mind about dragons.
他勸人很有一套
He can be really persuasive.
只要贏得龍的忠心
Once you've earned his loyalty,
他便會為你赴湯蹈火
there is nothing a dragon won't do for you.
你改變不了這里任何人的想法
You won't be changing any minds around here.
我此時此地就可以改變你的想法
I can change yours, right here, right now.
我可以嗎
Uh, may I?
-當心  -龍騎士
- Watch it! - Dragon riders!
放我下去
Put me down!
鼻涕嘮  你要干什么
Snotlout, what-what are you doing?
看我把你保護得多好
See how well I protect and provide?
那些網是干什么的
What is with all the nets?
小心  剛才真是...
Hey, watch it! That was...
危險
Close.
我的天吶
Oh, my.
我的菜啊
Me likey.
帶我走吧
Take me.
停止射擊
Hold your fire!
你們在這干什么
Um, what are you guys doing here?
我們來解救你
We're here to rescue you!
我不需要解救
I don't need to be rescued.
夠了
Enough!
你們是不是
Well, didn't you just pick
上錯船了
the wrong ship, eh?
我是艾瑞特  和我父親...
I am Eret, son of...
同名...
Eret...
我...
I...
把這家伙從我身上弄走
Get this thing off me.
還有誰
Anyone else?
我猜也是
Hmm, that's what I figured.
你  備龍鞍
You, saddle up.
我們回家
We're going home.
不
No.
簡直毫無責任心
Of all the irresponsible...
我要保護我們的龍  阻止一場戰爭
I'm trying to protect our dragons and stop a war.
這怎么能是不負責任呢
How is that irresponsible?
因為戰爭正是他想要的  兒子
Because war is what he wants, son!
多年前  有過一場盛大的首領聚會
Years ago, there was a great gathering of chieftains
專門討論我們當時面臨的龍災
to discuss the dragon scourge we all faced.
從我們中走出一位來自陌生大陸的陌生人
Into our midst came a stranger from a strange land,
渾身布滿傷疤  身披一頂龍皮斗篷
covered in scars and draped in a cloak of dragon skin.
他不帶武器
He carried no weapon
語氣柔和
and spoke softly,
說他叫
saying that he,
德拉戈·布達威斯
Drago Bludvist,
是一介平民
was a man of the people,
致力于從龍的奴役中解放人類
devoted to freeing mankind from the tyranny of dragons.
他說他僅憑一己之力就可以控制龍
He claimed that he alone could control the dragons,
他獨自一人就可以保證大家安全
and that he alone could keep us safe,
只要我們臣服于他
if we chose to bow down
追隨他
and follow him.
-愚蠢至極  -真好笑
- Stupid. - Ah, good one.
對  我們也笑了
Aye, we laughed, too...
直到他裹緊斗篷
Until he wrapped himself in his cloak
高喊著
and cried out,
那就等著瞧沒有我你們怎么辦
"Then see how well you do without me!"
等著瞧沒有我你們能怎么辦
...See how well you do without me!
房頂瞬間燃起大火
The rooftop suddenly burst into flames,
身披盔甲的龍從火中躥出
and from it, armored dragons descended,
把大廳燒成了灰
burning the hall to the ground.
我
I...
是唯一一個幸存者
was the only one to escape.
殺人不找理由的人不會和你講道理的
Men who kill without reason cannot be reasoned with.
-也許吧  -小嗝嗝
- Maybe. - Hiccup!
不過我還是要試試
I'm still going to try.
這是我所擅長的
This is what I'm good at,
既然我能改變你的想法
and-and if I could change your mind,
就能改變他的
I can change his, too.
出發
Come on.
-出發  -不
- Let's go. - No!
帶其他人回博克島去
Lead the others back to Berk.
這一天已經夠亂的了
I've had enough mutiny for one day.
好喜歡這個
Ooh, I like that.
暴芙奈
Ruffnut!
來了
Okay!
別擔心  伙計
Don't worry, bud.
我不會讓任何人傷害到你
I'm not gonna let anything happen to you.
我向你保證
I promise.
得了  爸爸
Aw, come on, dad.
沒完沒了了嗎
Really?
好吧
Okay.
別輕舉妄動
No sudden moves.
穩住  穩住
Hold on, hold on.
沒牙仔
Toothless...!
你把我的龍扔在那兒了
You left my dragon back there!
他自己不能飛  他會被淹死的
He can't fly on his own! He'll drown!
我們得調頭去找我的龍
We have to head back for my dragon!
你是誰
Who are you?
盜龍賊嗎
The dragon thief?
德拉戈·布達威斯嗎
Drago Bludvist?
你聽得懂
Do you even understand
我說話嗎
what I'm saying?
沒牙仔
Toothless!
沒事了  沒事了  沒事了
Oh, it's okay, it's okay, it's okay.
我也很高興見到你  伙計
I'm glad to see you, too, bud.
你真讓我擔心死了
You really had me worried there.
小嗝嗝
Hiccup?
這是真的嗎
C-could it be?
這么多年過去了
After all these years?
這怎么可能呢
How is this possible?
難道...
Uh, should I...
我認識你嗎
should I know you?
不
No.
你當時還是個嬰兒
You were only a babe.
但母親絕不會忘記自己的孩子
But a mother never forgets.
跟我來
Come.
倔脾氣
Boar-headed!
和他母親一模一樣
Just like his mother!
她也從不肯老實待著
Aye, she could never stay put, either.
他才二十歲嘛
Eh, he's just 20,
而且還是一個維京人
and a Viking.
這倆因素恐怕是最糟的組合了
I mean, could there be a worse combination?
想想你自己早年是有多么的
Heh! When I think of how stubborn and senseless
固執和愚蠢
you were back in the day.
天啊
Oh.
我看其實現在也沒變多少
Well, not much has changed, actually.
你也知道那孩子
Ah, you know what he's like.
他不會放棄的  戈伯
He won't give up, Gobber.
而且如果小嗝嗝在我們找到他之前
And if Hiccup finds Drago
就找到了德拉戈的話...
before we find him...
小嗝嗝不會有事的
Ah! Nothing can hurt Hiccup,
只要那條夜煞跟在他身邊
so long as that night fury's around.
那可是條夜煞啊
It's a night fury!
怎么了
Huh?
找到他們  裂顱
Find them, skullcrusher.
找到他們
Find them.
等等  稍等一下
Uh, h-hold on. Wait just a minute.
-這邊  -回來
- This way. - Come back here.
-來  -你不能
- Come. - You can't just say
說完那種話然后轉身就走
something like that and run off.
你是我媽媽
You're my mother?!
我是說  究竟怎么...
I mean, what the...?
你  你能理解這聽起來有多瘋狂嗎
Do you... do you grasp how insane it sounds?
快來
Come quickly.
我有話問你
I have questions!
這么些年你到底
Where have you...
去了哪里
been all this time?
你一直在做什么
What-what have you been doing?
但他們告訴我說你死掉了
But they-they said you were dead!
所有人都以為你是被龍吃掉...
Everyone thinks you were eaten by...
這就是你二十年來待的地方嗎
This is where you've been for 20 years?
你一直致力于拯救他們
You-you've been rescuing them.
簡直難以置信
Unbelievable.
-你不生氣嗎  -什么
- You're not upset? - What?
不  我不知道
No. I-I don't know. I...
說老實話  我還沒回過神來呢
It's a bit much to get my head around, to be Frank.
有點瘋狂兇猛的義務龍騎士自稱是我母親
It's not every day you find out your mother
這種事畢竟不是每天都會遇到的
is some kind of crazy, feral, vigilante dragon lady.
至少我并不無趣  對嗎
At least I'm not boring, right?
我想這點
Well, I suppose there is that...
確實如此
one specific thing.
你喜歡嗎
Do-do you like it?
我
I...
I... I...
我找不到合適的詞來表達
I-I don't have the words.
我能摸摸他嗎
C-can I...
他真美
Oh, he's beautiful.
驚艷絕世
Oh, incredible.
他很有可能就是他們種族的最后一只了
He might very well be the last of his kind.
瞧啊
Oh... and look,
他和你一樣大呢
he's your age.
怪不得你們這么合得來
No wonder you get along so well.
他的牙還可以收縮
And retractable teeth.
你怎么做到的
How did you manage...
我在樹林里發現了他
I found him in the woods.
他被打了下來  受了傷
He was shot down and wounded.
這只比齒龍因為
This snafflefang lost his leg
德拉戈·布達威斯的鐵捕龍夾丟了一條腿
to one of Drago Bludvist's iron traps.
這只止雨龍的翅膀
This raincutter
被剃刀網劃傷了
had her wing sliced by razor netting.
還有這只可憐的陸行龍
And this, oh, poor hobblegrunt
被一個樹枝陷阱弄瞎了
was blinded by a tree snare
在孤單害怕中被丟下等死
and then left to die alone and scared.
這是怎么回事
And what of this?
又是德拉戈和他的捕龍夾干的好事嗎
Did Drago or his trappers do this, too?
這個啊
Yeah.
奇葩的點在于
Well, crazy thing is...
把他打下來的人其實是我
I'm actually the one who shot him down.
不過沒事的
Hey, it's-it's okay, though.
他也報復我啦
He got me back.
對吧  伙計
Right, bud?
你就不能把我完整的救下來
You couldn't save all of me, could you?
非要跟我扯平不可
You just had to make it even.
所以才有了這假肢
So peg leg.
你父親對你這夜煞朋友是什么看法呢
What did your father think of your night fury friend?
一開始他不怎么接受
Oh, he-he didn't take it all that well.
不過后來  他改變了
But then, he changed.
大家都變了
They all did.
很快
Pretty soon,
家鄉的人都有了自己的龍
everyone back home had dragons of their own.
那怎么可能
If only it were possible.
不  是真的
No, really.
相信我吧  我也這樣嘗試過
Believe me, I tried, as well,
但是人們不會真的改變的  小嗝嗝
but people are not capable of change, Hiccup.
有些人
Some of us...
就是天生與眾不同
were just born different.
博克島當時面臨的命運
Berk was a land of kill
就是殺戮或被殺
or be killed,
但我當時相信和平的希望尚存
but I believed peace was possible.
住手  你這樣只會讓事情更糟
Stop! You'll only make it worse!
但沒人接受我的觀點
It was a very unpopular opinion.
小嗝嗝
Hiccup!
有一天
Then one night,
一條龍闖進了我們家  找到了
a dragon broke into our house, finding you
搖籃里的你
in the cradle.
我沖過去保護你
I rushed to protect you.
卻看到了證明我一直以來信仰的證據
But what I saw was proof of everything I believed.
他們不是殘暴的野獸
This wasn't a vicious beast,
他們是種聰明的  溫和的生物
but an intelligent, gentle creature,
我們的靈魂產生了共鳴
whose soul reflected my own.
-瓦爾卡  快跑  -不  不要
- Valka, run! - No, don't.
堅持住
Hold on!
不要  史推克
No! Aah! Stoick!
瓦爾卡
Valka!
史推克
Stoick!
瓦爾卡
Valka.
那晚你和你父親
You and your father nearly died
差點喪命
that night.
只因為我不忍心殺死一條龍
All because I couldn't kill a dragon.
家族遺傳啊
Eh, runs in the family.
離開你們讓我心碎
It broke my heart to stay away,
但我想只有如此你們才更安全
but I believed you'd be safer if I did.
你是怎么活下來的呢
How did you survive?
躍云并沒想傷害我
Oh, cloudjumper never meant to harm me.
他肯定是覺得我屬于這里
He must have thought I belonged here
這個令人炫目的野獸之家
in the home of the great bewilder beast.
阿爾法族
The Alpha species.
世上所剩無幾的
One of the very few
其中之一了
that still exist.
每個龍巢都有龍后
Every nest has its queen,
但他才是龍族之王
but this is the king of all dragons.
他可以噴出冰
With his icy breath,
這只美麗的巨獸就這樣為我們建起了龍巢
this graceful giant built our nest,
一個所有龍族都可以安然居住的天堂
a safe haven for dragons everywhere.
等等  那就是噴冰龍嗎
Wait, that's the ice-spitter?
那個被摧毀的堡壘
He's responsible
就是他干的嗎
for all that destruction?
他保護著我們
He protects us.
我們受他保護
We all live under his care
并聽令于他
and his command.
當然  除了龍寶寶
All but the babies, of course...
因為龍寶寶誰的話也不聽
who listen to no one.
我和他們住在一起二十年了  小嗝嗝
I've lived among them for 20 years, Hiccup,
探索著他們的秘密
discovering their secrets.
他喜歡你
He likes you.
你一定餓了吧
You must be hungry.
有點  吃點東西也好
Uh, yeah, I could eat.
太好了
Good.
因為用餐時間到了
It's feeding time.
我感覺不好
I don't like it.
他們早該找到小嗝嗝一起回來了
They should've been back with Hiccup by now.
我也不開心
I don't like it, either.
與他父親同名的艾瑞特
Eret, son of Eret,
就是我的夢中情人
was the man of my dreams.
我的一切
My everything!
可是寶貝  我都為你留了胡子啊
But, baby, I grew facial hair for you.
我也是
Me, too.
如果他們被德拉戈打下來了怎么辦
What if Drago shot them down?
說不定他們需要我們幫忙
What if they need our help?
我們得去找他們
We have to find them.
等等  什么
Wait, wait, what?
不行  史推克說
No, but Stoick said...
要是他們真被抓了
It doesn't matter what he said
不管他說過什么都不重要了
if they've all been captured.
走吧
Come on!
我們要回去嗎
Do we go back?
我們現在無處可去
We've nowhere to go,
無貨可賣  而且都
nothing to sell, and no heads
性命難保了
to call our own.
-艾瑞特  -如果我們不快點
- Uh, Eret...? - If we don't turn up
找到幾只龍的話
with dragons and fast...
許愿時要小心哦
Careful what you wish for!
-想想辦法  -艾瑞特
- Do something! - Eret, son of Eret!
我們會想念你的  艾瑞特
We'll miss you, Eret!
搞什么啊
What is this?
綁架你啊
A kidnapping.
我帶他飛行嗎  行嗎
Yay, can he ride with me? Can he?
行嗎
Can he...?
你帶我們去找德拉戈
You're gonna show us the way to Drago.
然后幫龍騎士
And help dragon riders
偷偷溜進德拉戈的營地嗎
sneak into Drago's camp?
還是現在殺了我算了
Just kill me now.
沒問題啊
That could be arranged.
風中飛  放開他
Stormfly, drop it.
什么
Huh?
好樣的
Good girl!
風中飛  抓住他
Stormfly, fetch.
好吧
All right!
好吧  我帶你們去找德拉戈
Okay! I'll take you to Drago!
百試不爽
Works every time.
我們不是要去吃東西嗎
Hey, I-I thought we were going to eat.
是啊
Oh, we are.
之后  從龍之島開始
And then, from Dragon Island,
我又發現了這些群島
I found this archipelago...
好了
There.
每次我身處高空
Oh, when I'm up here,
甚至都感覺不到寒冷
I don't even feel the cold.
完全沉浸在...
I just feel...
自由里
Free.
這就是
This is what it is
成為龍的感覺  小嗝嗝
to be a dragon, Hiccup.
你完全可以
It's all well and good
自稱為龍
to call yourself a dragon,
不過你能飛嗎
but can you fly?
哦不
Oh, no!
伙計  真是千鈞一發
Man, almost!
我們這次差點就成功了
We just about had it that time.
棒極了
Incredible.
你也不賴
Well, not bad yourself.
這么多年以來  你竟然這么像我
All this time, you took after me.
可是
And...
我卻在哪里
where was I?
我真的非常抱歉  小嗝嗝
I'm so sorry, Hiccup.
我們重頭再來可以嗎
Can we start over?
你能再給我一次機會嗎
Will you give me another chance?
我  我可以教你這二十年來
I-I can teach you all that I've learned
我學到的一切
these past 20 years.
比如...
Like...
現在你可以做急轉彎了
Now you can make those tight turns.
你知道你能這樣嗎
Did you know about this?
每種龍
Every dragon
都有自己獨特的秘密  而且
has its secrets. And...
我會把這些都教給你
I'll show them all to you.
我們可以解開所有的謎題
We'll unlock every mystery,
找到所有種族  母與子  我們倆一起
find every last species... together, as mother and son.
我們共同擁有的這個天賦  小嗝嗝
This gift we share, Hiccup,
把我們緊緊聯系在了一起
it bonds us.
這才是真實的你  兒子
This is who you are, son.
真實的我們
Who we are.
我們可以改變龍族的世界
We will change the world for all dragons.
把它變的更好更安全
We will make it a better, safer place.
好啊  我是說
Yeah, I mean,
聽起來很棒
that sounds amazing.
這簡直太棒了
Oh, this is so great!
你可以和我一起去和德拉戈談談
Now you and I can go talk to Drago together.
什么
What?
跟德拉戈沒什么好談的
There's no talking to Drago.
-但我們得  -不行
- But we have to... - No.
我們必須保護我們的龍
We must protect our own.
走吧
Come on.
我們該回去了
We should be getting back.
好了  我已經把你們帶來了
Okay, I got you here!
快把這家伙弄走
Now get this thing off me.
永遠不要和龍搶玩具
Never take a toy from a dragon.
你怎么什么都不懂
Don't you know anything?
為什么倒霉的總是我
Why does this keep happening to me?
那下面是什么啊
What's down there?
吐出的水泡直徑很大
Large diameter bubbles,
說明肺部巨大
massive lungs,
居住在深海冰水里  我想
cold water deep dweller, I'm thinking
應該是五級巨獸
class five leviathan,
或許有六級
maybe six.
肉球  你怎么了  寶貝
Meatlug, what's wrong, girl?
鉤牙  振作啊
Hookfang! Come on!
不許動
Don't move!
德拉戈
Drago!
放開我
Get off me!
見到你總是很高興  我的朋友
Always great to see you, my friend.
在這兒取暖呢
Keeping warm up here?
如你所見  我可是準時
Well, as you can see, I am right on time
帶了一批新龍過來哦
with a new batch of dragons,
和我保證的一樣
just like I promised.
他要醒過來了  拉住他
He's waking up! Drop the ropes!
來人支援一下
Give me some backup here!
小心
Watch out!
放下繩子
Drop the ropes.
鉤牙
Hookfang!
你在干什么
What are you doing?!
你如今屬于我了
You belong to me now.
另外作為額外贈送的禮物
And as an added bonus,
我還把他們的騎手給你抓來了
I also caught you their riders.
不另外收費哦
No extra charge.
什么  你在開什么玩笑
What? Are you kidding me?
但你之前真是太完美了
But you were so perfect!
我后來發現  有好大一群龍騎士
Turns out there's a whole bunch of them out there.
他們攻擊了...
They attacked...
有多少
How many?
原來德拉戈沒抓住他們
Drago doesn't have them after all.
-有多少  -上百個
- How many? - Hundreds.
有滿滿一島的人呢
A whole island full.
我倒是不擔心
I wouldn't worry about it.
說話這會兒我的人就在追捕他們呢
My men are hunting them down as we speak.
他們不會發現你的藏身之處的
They won't know where you're hiding.
我向你保證
I promise you that.
他們會發現的  他們知道我們失蹤了
Oh, yes, they will! They know we're missing,
而且他們有會追蹤的龍
and they have tracking dragons.
如果你敢碰我們  小嗝嗝會狠狠揍...
If you so much as touch us, Hiccup is gonna kick...
-小嗝嗝  -他不會壞你的事兒的
- Hiccup? - He's not a problem.
真的  相信我
Really, trust me.
他是偉岸的史推克之子
He's only the son of Stoick the Vast,
是博克島首領的繼承人
his heir to the throne of Berk,
還是有史以來最棒的馴龍大師
and the greatest dragon master this world has ever seen.
馴龍大師
"Dragon master"?
我是唯一一個能控制龍的人
I alone control the dragons.
-并不是呢  -不好意思哦
- Nope, mm-mm. - Sorry!
除非你放我們走  馬上就放
And unless you let us go right now,
不然他將會騎著他的夜煞襲卷這里
he will blast through here on his Night Fury
然后把你的整支船隊
and blow your entire fleet of ships
卷成碎片
to splinters.
然后他們會像小寶寶一樣哭泣
Then they'll be crying like babies.
真是幽默風趣
Funny and beautiful.
說得好  寶貝兒
Good one, babe.
沒錯  像小寶寶一樣哭泣
Yeah. Like babies.
他們總是哭個不停
They always cry.
真是群小不點
Real tiny ones.
起先  你說只有一個龍騎士
First there was one rider,
現在整個博克島都是了
and now all of Berk?
而且你還帶著他們找上門來了
And you led them to me!
德拉戈
Drago...!
停下一切準備工作
Stop all preparations!
我們必須得馬上出擊龍騎士的老巢
We must attack the dragon riders' nest at once!
我們要干掉他們龍王
We will take down their Alpha.
然后占領整個博克島
Then we will take Berk!
德拉戈
Drago!
干掉他
And get rid of him.
德拉戈  拜托  我...
Drago, please, I...
風中飛
Stormfly!
不
No!
伙計...
Well, bud...
我們不能等著德拉戈來攻擊這地方
We can't wait around for Drago to attack this place.
我們得先一步找到他
We've got to find him first.
走吧
Let's go.
淡定
Easy now.
你開什么玩笑  你是怎么進來這里的
Are you kidding me? How did you get in here?
我們怎么進來就怎么出去
The same way we're getting you out.
-我們  -安全
- "We"? - All clear.
-沒牙仔  跟上  -等等  等等
- Toothless, come. - Uh, wait, uh, wait...
好吧  爸  有...有件事你得知道
Okay, uh, dad, there-there's something you need to know.
行  行  路上再說
Yeah, yeah, tell me on the way.
這可不是什么可以"路上再說"的問題
Well, this isn't an "on the way" kind of update, actually.
我不想再聽了  小嗝嗝
I've heard enough, Hiccup.
還有更多驚天動地的
More-more of the earth-shattering
事件發展和變化
development variety.
是啊是啊  又一件
Yeah, just add it to pile.
沒錯  我
Yeah, I,
爸  和其他大部分我告訴你的"驚喜"不同
dad, unlike most surprises I spring on you,
我保證你會喜歡這個的
this is one you'll like, I promise.
只不過你需要小心消化一下
You just have to handle it delicately.
所以...
So...
也許你會想自己處理一下這個
You might want to take this one.
什么
Huh?
天啊
Oh, boy.
爸爸  能請您把劍放下嗎
Dad, could you put the sword away, please?
我知道你想要說什么  史推克
I know what you're gonna say, Stoick.
我怎么能那么做
How could I have done this?
這些年來一直躲在外面
Stayed away all of these years,
還有為什么我沒有回到你身邊
and why didn't I come back to you?
回到兒子身邊
To our son?
我看到了任何你可能會改變的希望嗎  史推克
What sign did I have that you could change, Stoick?
或者是博克島的人可能會改變的希望
That anyone on Berk could?
我祈求了這么多次
I pleaded so many times
希望你們停止戰爭  去尋找其他解決方法
to stop the fighting, to find another answer,
但是你們有人聽過我的話嗎
but did any of you listen?
這就是我不結婚的原因
This is why I never married.
這是一個原因  還有另一個
This, and one other reason.
我知道我留你獨自一個人撫養小嗝嗝
I know that I left you to raise Hiccup alone,
但我想著沒有我在身邊  他會更好
but I thought he'd be better off without me,
但是我錯了
and I was wrong.
如今我看清了這一點  但是...
I see that now, but...
別這么一言不發的  史推克
Stop being so stoic, Stoick.
快啊
Go on,
大吼  大叫  說點什么
shout, scream, say something!
你還是和我失去你的那天一般美麗
You're as beautiful as the day I lost you.
這一天還能更糟糕嗎
Could this day get any worse?
讓我瞧瞧
Uh, let me see.
我們就要跳進冰冷的水里
We're gonna jump into freezing cold water
然后被淹死了
and then die from drowning.
看起來真涼爽
Looks refreshing.
請吧  女士優先
Please, ladies first.
你就是一坨龍大便
You are a steaming heap of dragon.
蹲下
Duck.
快去警告其他人
Warn the others!
抓住他們  艾瑞特
Get them, you son of an Eret.
接招
Take that!
好吧  我再次愛上了你
Okay, I love you again.
真是可悲呀
Oh, pathetic.
你還可以去跳海
You can still jump.
我們還要不要去救出你們的龍
So, are we going to save your dragons
然后逃離這里了
and get out of here or not?
檢查每一個捕龍夾
Check every trap.
他們就在這兒的某個地方
They're here somewhere.
肉球
Meatlug?
有人往這邊來了嗎
Anyone coming?
不知道  你繼續做手頭上的事就好
I don't know, you just keep doing what you're doing.
繼續轉
Keep cranking.
謝謝你救了我一命
Thank you for saving my life.
現在讓我還你一個人情吧
Now let me return the favor.
媽媽  你絕對會認不出來那個地方的
Mom, you'd never even recognize it.
過去我們造武器的地方
Where we used to make weapons,
如今用來造龍鞍
we now build saddles,
翅蹬
wing slings...
我們...我們甚至還給龍補牙
We-we even fix dragon teeth.
你不會相信一切的變化是有多大
You-you wouldn't believe how much everything's changed.
是呀  你兒子把博克島變得更好了
Aye, your son's changed Berk for the better.
我覺得這件事上我們做得不錯  瓦爾卡
I think we did well with this one, Val.
謝謝爸爸
Thanks, dad.
我來
I got it.
我...
I'm, uh...
有點生疏了
a little out of practice.
你知道的
Well, you know,
我又不是因為你的廚藝才娶你的
I didn't marry you for your cooking.
希望不是
I hope not.
她做的肉丸  殺傷力比一把戰斧都大
Her meatballs could kill more beasts than a battle ax.
我的肚子對她的肉丸可一直印象深刻呢
I've still got a few knocking around in here.
只要你帶著你所有的龍一起回來
And once you move back in with all your dragons,
老德拉戈根本毫無勝算
old Drago won't even stand a chance.
一切都會順順利利的
Everything will be okay.
慢點  兒子
Slow down, son.
還有很多需要考慮的事情
It's a lot to take in.
我明白了
Oh, gotcha.
我愛死這個了
Oh, I love this one.
還記得我們的歌嗎  瓦爾卡
Remember our song, Val?
我將暢游航行在茫茫大海中
I'll swim and sail on savage seas
不曾畏懼巨浪淹沒我
With ne'er a fear of drowning
歡樂地駕馭著生活的波濤
And gladly ride the waves of life
只要你愿嫁給我
If you will marry me
無論炙熱的太陽
No scorching sun
或是刺骨的寒涼
Nor freezing cold
都不會...
Will...
都不會阻擋我的...步...伐...
Will stop me on my... journey
不好意思
Sorry.
只要你許我你的芳心
If you will promise me your heart
并且愛...
And love...
并且愛我永不停
And love me for eternity
我最親愛的我的寶貝
My dearest one my darling dear
你話語擲地有聲震撼我
Your mighty words astound me
但我并不需要這些海誓山盟
But I've no need of mighty deeds
只要你的臂彎環繞我
When I feel your arms around me
但我愿送你金戒指
But I would bring you rings of gold
也愿為你吟歌唱詩
And even sing you poetry
真的嗎
Oh, would you?
我會護你遠離一切災難
And I would keep you from all harm
只要你愿待在我身旁
If you would stay beside me
金戒指對我沒有用
I have no use for rings of gold
我也不欣賞你的詩
I care not for your poetry
我只希望能牽著你的手
I only want your hand to hold
我只希望你在我身旁
I only want you near me
愛你  吻你  緊擁你
To love and kiss, to sweetly hold
與你共舞  共入夢鄉
For the dancing and the dreaming
一起走過風風雨雨
Through all life's toils and delights
我將把你的笑容珍藏在身側
I'll keep your laugh inside me
我將暢游航行在茫茫大海中
I'll swim and sail the savage seas
不曾畏懼巨浪淹沒我
With ne'er a fear of drowning
歡樂地駕馭著生活的波濤
And gladly ride the waves of life
只要你愿嫁給我
If you will marry me
-我還在堅持唱哦...  -戈伯
- I'm still going... - Gobber.
我唱完了
I'm done.
我還以為至死也不能與你共舞了呢
I thought I'd have to die before we'd have that dance again.
沒必要給我下猛藥啦
No need for drastic measures.
為了你  我親愛的...
For you, my dear...
我愿意做任何事
Anything.
你愿意回家嗎  瓦爾卡
Will you come home, Val?
你愿意重新成為我的妻子嗎
Will you be my wife once again?
我們可以重組一個家庭
We can be a family!
你愿意嗎
What do you say?
我愿意
Yes.
太棒了  以后做飯我來
Great! I'll do the cooking.
感謝奧丁神你沒聽我的話  兒子
Thank Odin you didn't listen to me, son.
不然我們永遠都找不到對方了
We never would've found each other.
沒牙仔
Toothless?
發生什么事了
What's happening?
不...
Oh, no...
瓦爾卡...
Val...
瓦爾卡  沒事的  沒事的
Val, it's all right, it's all right.
我們現在是一個團隊了
We're a team now.
現在  你想怎么辦
Now, what do you want to do?
我們得拯救那些龍
We have to save the dragons.
好的  沒問題
Aye, you got it.
來吧  兒子
Come on, son!
裝彈
Reload!
開火
Fire!
開火  開火
Fire! Fire!
不管任何代價  堅持進攻那座山
Whatever comes, keep hitting the Mountain.
我們得把龍王引出來
We need to draw the Alpha out.
準備好捕龍夾
Ready the traps!
驚喜
Surprise!
好耶
Yeah!
什么
What?!
你身上還真是驚喜連連呢
You really are full of surprises.
走吧
Let's go.
龍騎士駕到
Dragon riders coming through!
噴火
Fire!
太好了
Oh, yeah!
把他們砍下來
Cut them down!
和父親同名的艾瑞特
Eret, son of Eret!
往上飛  姑娘
Up, girl!
向左傾斜  艾瑞特
Lean left, Eret!
就是這樣
That's it!
小心
Look out!
耶  寶貝兒
Yeah, baby!
干掉他們
Take them down!
當心哦[雙關為"抬頭"]
Heads up!
馴龍大師
Dragon master.
歡迎加入  龍騎士
Welcome aboard, dragon rider.
我得說  謝謝
Thanks. I think.
你去哪兒了
Where have you been?
和媽媽敘敘舊
Oh, you know, catching up with mom.
那是你媽媽
That's your mother?!
現在你知道我的表演天賦是從哪來的了吧
Well, now you know where I get my dramatic flair.
龍王
The Alpha!
我們有場硬仗要打了
Now we have a fight!
來吧  沒牙仔
Come on, Toothless.
讓他們瞧瞧你的厲害  伙計
Show them what you got, bud.
好樣的
Attaboy!
這一刻我等了許久了
I've waited a long time for this.
你無法奪走我們的龍
You cannot take our dragons!
他們是由龍王控制的
They are controlled by the Alpha!
還好我帶來了一位挑戰者
Then it's a good thing I brought a challenger.
另一只龍王
Another one?
那可是只十級的龍  十級的
That is a class ten! Class ten!
小心
Look out!
-不...不要...  -來吧
- No... no... - Come on!
干掉那只龍王
Take down the Alpha!
不要
No!
謝謝
Thank you.
為了你  我親愛的...
For you, my dear...
我愿意做任何事
Anything.
瓦爾卡  你覺得你能阻止他們嗎
Val, do you think you can stop them?
我會盡力的  來吧  躍云
I'll do my best. Come on, Cloudjumper!
你
You!
我看著你被燒著了
I watched you burn!
想殺我這點火還不夠
It takes more than a little fire to kill me!
史推克
Stoick!
不要
No!
我們贏了
We've won.
現在...
Now...
干掉她
Finish her!
不要
No!
堅持住
Hold on!
沖啊  裂顱
Skullcrusher, go!
跟上  戈伯
Come on, Gobber!
緊緊跟在你后面呢  史推克
Right behind you, Stoick!
停下
Stop!
這...就是所謂的馴龍大師嗎
This... is the great dragon master?
偉岸的史推克之子嗎
The son of Stoick the Vast?
他該感到多羞愧啊
What shame he must feel.
所有這些傷害...
All of this loss...
都為了些什么
And for what?
就為了變得無人能敵嗎
To become unstoppable?
就為了統治世界嗎
To rule the world?
龍  他們...他們是善良的
Dragons, they-they are kind,
神奇的生物  能與人類和平相處
amazing creatures that can bring people together.
或者傷害人類
Or tear them apart.
你瞧  我知道生活在恐懼中是什么滋味
You see, I know what it is to live in fear,
知道自己的村莊被焚毀
to see my village burned,
家庭被毀滅是什么滋味
my family taken.
但是即便小時候
But even as a boy
我無依無靠
left with nothing,
我也發誓要
I vowed to rise above
戰勝對龍的恐懼
the fear of dragons
并且解放這世上所有的人
and liberate the people of this world.
那為什么要組建龍族軍隊
Then why a dragon army?
你要用龍來戰勝其它龍
Well, you need dragons to conquer other dragons.
又或者你是要用龍來征服人類
Or maybe you need dragons to conquer people
來控制追隨你的人
to control those who follow you
消滅違抗你的人
and to get rid of those who won't.
聰明
Clever boy.
世界需要和平
The world wants peace,
博克島已經找到了人龍和平共處的方式
and we have the answer back on Berk.
讓我展示給你看吧
Just... let me show you...
不
No!
還是讓我
Let me
展示給你看看吧
show you!
搞什么
What in...
小嗝嗝
Hiccup!
快來  戈伯
Come on, Gobber!
好吧  計劃有變
Okay, change of plan.
任何龍都無法違抗龍王的命令
No dragon can resist the Alpha's command.
所以誰控制了龍王
So he who controls the Alpha
也就控制了所有龍
controls them all.
沒牙仔
Toothless?
沒牙仔  你沒事吧  伙計  怎么了
T-toothless, you okay, bud? What's going on?
讓你見識一下真正的厲害
Witness true strength.
控制其它龍的強大意念力
The strength of will over others.
與之相比
In the face of it,
你微不足道
you are nothing.
他剛剛跟你說了什么
Uh... what did he just tell you?
沒牙仔  拜托
Toothless, come on.
你怎么了
What's the matter with you?
不  不  不  拜托  你這是干嗎
No, no, no, no, come on, what are you doing?
別這樣
Knock it off.
停  快醒過來
Stop! Snap out of it!
沒牙仔  不要
Toothless, no!
沒牙仔
Toothless!
-不要  -小嗝嗝
- Don't! - Hiccup!
-住手  -兒子
- Stop...! - Son!
爸
Dad!
別過來
No!
不
No...
爸
Dad!
史推克
Stoick...
爸
Dad?
不  你
No. You...
不
No.
不  不  不  不
No, no, no. No.
不  別碰他
No! Get away from him!
走  走開
Go on! Get out of here!
走開
Get away!
這不是他的錯
It's not his fault.
你心里清楚
You know that.
馴良的龍
Good dragons
在壞人的控制下
under the control of bad people...
-不  等等  別走  -也會做壞事
- No, wait. Don't go. - do bad things.
快點
Come on!
召集所有人在博克島會合
Gather the men and meet me at Berk!
-沒牙仔  -不  別去
- Toothless! - No, don't.
愿武神迎接你
May the Valkyries welcome you
引領你穿過奧丁的偉大戰場
and lead you through Odin's great battlefield.
愿他們用愛和狂怒歌唱你的名字
May they sing your name with love and fury,
讓我們聽到由瓦爾哈拉殿堂深處傳來的頌歌
so that we might hear it rise from the depths of Valhalla,
北歐神話主神兼死亡之神奧丁接待英靈的殿堂
在國王之桌上
and know that you've taken your rightful place
你已獲得了應有的席位
at the table of kings.
一位偉人從此隕落
For a great man has fallen.
他同時也是一名勇士
A warrior.
一位族長
A chieftain.
一位慈父
A father.
和一位摯友
A friend.
對不起  爸
I'm sorry, dad.
我沒能成為
I'm not the chief that
你期望中的領袖
you wanted me to be.
也沒能像我想象中那樣捍衛和平
And I'm not the peacekeeper I thought I was.
我  不知道
I... don't know...
你是個早產兒
You came early into this world.
你出生的時候個子好小
You were such a wee thing.
是那么脆弱  那么不堪一擊
Oh, so frail, so fragile.
我害怕你會夭折
I feared you wouldn't make it.
但是你父親
But your father...
他從未懷疑過
he never doubted.
他總說你會成為他們之中最強壯的一個
He always said you'd become the strongest of them all.
他說對了
And he was right.
你擁有領袖的心胸
You have the heart of a chief,
和龍的靈魂
and the soul of a dragon.
只有你才能把我們的世界維系起來
Only you can bring our worlds together.
你就是這樣的人  兒子
That... is who you are, son.
我
I, uh...
我曾好怕變成父親那樣
I was so afraid of becoming my dad.
因為我覺得我將永遠無法做到像他那樣
Mostly because I thought I never could.
酒精怎么才能成為一個
How-how do you become someone...
那么偉大  那么勇敢
that great, that... brave,
那么無私的人呢
that... selfless?
我想我只有盡力了
I guess you can only try.
首領要保衛自己的領土
A chief protects his own.
我們要回去
We're going back.
-怎么回  -他把所有龍都帶走了
- Uh... with what? - Uh, he took all the dragons.
不是所有龍
Not all of them.
我還不想死啊
I don't want to die!
我們根本沒辦法控制這些家伙
We can't fly these things!
是啊  就是說啊
Yeah, no kidding!
可是那只龍王
But won't that bewilder beast
不會也把這些小家伙給控制了嗎
just take control of these guys, too?
他們是龍寶寶  才不會聽任何人的呢
They're babies! They don't listen to anyone.
是啊  就像我們一樣
Yeah. Just like us.
這實在是  太危險了
This is... whoa... very dangerous!
有些人可能會說
Some might suggest
這主意糟透了
this is poorly conceived!
還好我從不聽話
Well, it's a good thing that I never listen.
那你
So
到底有什么
what is your...
計劃
plan?
奪回沒牙仔  狠狠教訓德拉戈
Get Toothless back and kick Drago's...
小心
Heads up!
還有這件事
And that thing.
好孩子
Ah, that's a good boy.
看  看著點家具
W-w-watch the furniture!
你要去哪
Where are you going?
你們的首領已經死了
Your chief... is dead!
-史推克  -不  不可能
- Stoick? - No! Not possible!
現在沒人能保護你們了
No one can protect you now!
不
No.
他帶走了所有龍
He took all the dragons.
引開龍王
Distract the Alpha.
讓他無暇顧及沒牙仔
Try to keep his focus off of Toothless.
怎么引開他啊
Uh, how?
你忘了你的戰斗伙伴是誰了嗎
Have you forgotten who you're riding with?
就沒有我馴服不了的龍
There isn't a dragon alive that I can't wrangle! Aah!
-這只除外  -半吊子
- Except for this one...! - Amateur.
看啊  是小嗝嗝
Hey, look! It's Hiccup!
什么
What?
繼續扔羊
Keep 'em coming!
黑羊來了  寶貝
Black sheep, baby!
十分
Ten points!
我沒事
I'm okay!
我承認  想甩掉你還真不容易
You certainly are hard to get rid of, I'll say that.
沒牙仔
Toothless...
是我  伙計
It's me, bud.
是我
It's me.
是我  我在這呢  伙計
It's me. I'm right here, bud.
回我這來
Come back to me.
他已經不是你的了
He's not yours anymore.
他現在屬于龍王
He belongs to the Alpha.
但是  請便吧  馴龍大師
But, please, o great dragon master,
你可以試試
try... to take him.
他第二次可不會失手了
He will not miss a second time.
那不是你的錯  伙計
It wasn't your fault, bud.
是他們逼你做的
They... made you do it.
你永遠也不會傷害他的
You'd never hurt him.
你永遠也不會傷害我的
You'd never hurt me.
你是怎么做到的
How are you doing that?
求求你了  你是我最好的朋友  伙計
Please. You are my best friend, bud.
我最好的朋友
My best friend.
好樣的  這就對啦
Attaboy! That's it!
我就在這兒
I'm here.
夠了
Enough!
堅持住
Hang on!
我快夠到你了  伙計  我這就來了
Almost there, buddy, almost there.
想想辦法啊
Do something!
我們得把他們倆分開
We need to get those two apart.
我們必須屏蔽掉控制  沒牙仔
We gotta block him out, Toothless.
你信任我嗎  伙計
Do you trust me, bud?
我們能做到的
We can do this.
你和我
You... and me...
一心同體
as one.
沒錯
That's it.
咱倆再試一次
Now let's try this one more time!
打敗他  寶貝
Take him down, babe!
去打敗他
Go get him.
控制它啊
Take control of it!
別受他干擾  沒牙仔
Shut it out, Toothless.
-阻止他們  -就是現在
- Stop them! - Now!
又來
Not again.
沒牙仔  成敗就看現在了
Toothless, it's now or never!
來啊  伙計
Come on, bud!
穩住
Hold on!
我們成功了
Ya-ha! We did it!
盯住他  沒牙仔
Hold him there, Toothless.
一切都結束了
It's all over now.
是嗎
Or is it?
不
Oh, no!
No!
不
小嗝嗝
Hiccup...
他在挑戰龍王
He's challenging the Alpha!
為了保護你
To protect you!
不  不  不  不  不  不
No, no, no, no, no! No!
反擊啊  反擊
Fight back! Fight!
反擊
Fight!
你這是怎么了
What's the matter with you!
堅守陣地  決不動搖
Hold your ground! Hold the line now!
你現在明白了嗎
Now do you get it?
這才叫贏得了龍的真心
This is what it is to earn a dragon's loyalty.
讓這一切就此結束吧
Let this end now.
永不
Never!
上啊
Come on!
反擊
Fight!
真正的龍王會保護所有的龍
The Alpha... protects them all.
你總是讓我刮目相看  伙計
You never cease to amaze me, bud.
謝謝
Thank you.
沒牙仔  你知道口水洗不掉
Toothless, you know that doesn't wash out!
我就知道你會回來的
I knew you'd come back
你回來了  寶貝
You're back, my beauty!
風中飛
Stormfly!
讓我抱抱  葛倫普
Oh, give me a cuddle, Grumpy!
誰是我的小公主
Who's my little princess!
你再也不許離開我了  鉤牙
Don't you ever leave again, Hookfang.
-就是你  沒錯  就是你  -想死你了
- Oh, you are. Yes, you are. - I missed you...
噴噴
Oh, Barf...
不是你
Not you!
剛才的你
That was some
馴龍果然很有一套啊
pretty fine dragon-wrangling back there.
你會是個出色的捕龍獵手
You'd make a good trapper.
裂顱現在需要找個人
You know... Skullcrusher is gonna need somebody
照顧他
to look after him now.
我嗎
Me?
我很榮幸
I'd be honored.
你父親
Oh, your father,
會像我一樣為你自豪的
he'd be every bit as proud as I am.
謝謝
Thank you.
你在我身邊真是太好了  媽媽
I'm really glad you're here, mom.
我會一直留在你身邊的
And here I'll stay.
看吧
See?
我就說在這里吧
I told you it was in here.
你還玩這招呢
You're still doing that one.
真好笑
That's hilarious.
你給我過來
Come here, you.
首領歸來
The chief has come home!
首領萬歲
Long live the chief!
首領萬歲  首領萬歲
Long live the chief! Long live the chief!
首領萬歲
Long live the chief!
這里是博克島
This... is Berk.
有些破爛  有些簡陋
A bit trampled and busted
還有些地方被冰覆蓋  但這里是我的家
and covered in ice, but it's home.
是我們的家
It's our home.
過往襲擊過我們的敵人
Those who attacked us
殘酷且瘋狂
are relentless and crazy.
但是成功戰勝了他們的我們呢
But those who stopped them?
更是勇猛
Oh... even more so!
雖然我們人數不多  但是我們象征著
We may be small in numbers, but we stand for something
這個世界上最強大的東西
bigger than anything the world can pit against us.
我們代表和平的聲音
We are the voice of peace.
我們終將一點點改變這個世界
And bit by bit, we will change this world.
我們有他們所缺少的東西
You see, we have something they don't.
的確  他們有軍隊
Oh, sure, they have armies,
有艦隊  但是我們
and they have armadas, but we...
我們有
We have...
我們的龍
our dragons!